<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An expositio[n] of the .4. chap. of S. Joans Reuelation made by Bar. Traheron, in sondrie readinges before his countre men in Germanie. Where in the prouide[n]ce of God is treated with an annswer made to the obiection of a gentle aduersarie</title>
            <title>Exposition of the .4. chap. of S. Joans Revelation.</title>
            <author>Traheron, Bartholomew, 1510?-1558?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 942:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An expositio[n] of the .4. chap. of S. Joans Reuelation made by Bar. Traheron, in sondrie readinges before his countre men in Germanie. Where in the prouide[n]ce of God is treated with an annswer made to the obiection of a gentle aduersarie</title>
                  <title>Exposition of the .4. chap. of S. Joans Revelation.</title>
                  <author>Traheron, Bartholomew, 1510?-1558?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>P. A. de Zuttere?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted Anno .1557. [i.e. 1558]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: 1558.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation IV --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5636:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5636:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>An Expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the .4. chap. of. S. Ioans Reuelation ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by Bar. Traheron in ſondrie Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges before his countre men in Germanie. Where in the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God is treated with an aunſwer made to the obiections of a gentle aduerſarie.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted Anno. 1557.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5636:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5636:2"/>
            <head>To maſter Ro. Parker / and to maiſtres An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne his godlie wife / exiles for Chriſtes cauſe / Bar. Traheron wiſheth encreaſe of goddes grace.</head>
            <p>VvHile I labored to conforte my ſelfe / and other in the conſideration of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / you know how one put in his fote / and aſſaied to impugne / ſome parte of that / that I had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though bi your procure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we met together / and after ſome debatinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon the cheife pointes / that before ſemed to be in controuerſie betwene vs / yet afterward it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him to ſhew certaine reaſons againſt my affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation / ether for exerciſe of lerninge / or bicaufe he wold be better confirmed in the truth. Now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deringe that the matter is of great weight / &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaunce / and ſomewhat ſcrupulous in this wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes of mennes capacitee / and ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions / and cauillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of licen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious heddes / leſt anie thinge ſhuld be bruted otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / I haue thought good to putte in pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te al that I ſaid in your preſence / that al men maie know / what my meaninge is / not by reherſal ſermons / but by mine awne writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. And in this behalfe I haue par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely folowed the counſel of M. Gilbert Barkley / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you know I haue in due reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / for his great grauite / and ſingular integrite of life. This poore
<pb facs="tcp:5636:3"/> frute of my ſtudies I dedicate vnto you my moſt en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tierly biloued maſter Parker / and to the right wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie matrone your wife. For ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the perfecte ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re loue / that ſhuld be betwene al maried folke / ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth moſt notably in you / I wold not ſondre you in this place / whom god hath ſo ioigned / and made one in al good thinges. I haue iudged it alſo my du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie for aſmuch as the bowels of the ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctes haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and be daily refreſhed by you / to rendre this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of your ſingular godlines / and of my good affection towardes you / in the ſight of the world. God almightie confirme / and augmente in you the knowlege of his truth / and loue of righteouſnes / &amp; bleſſe my biloued / We<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tworth / Peregrine / An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / &amp; Cecile your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that they maie fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the godlie ſteppes of their Paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / and that the mention that I make of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this place / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie be a ſpurre vnto them here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſet them forewarde in the loue of tru religion / and innocentie of life.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5636:3"/>
            <div type="reading">
               <head>¶THE FIRST READINGE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>As</hi> THE viſion which Ezechiel ſaw / and deſcribeth in the .1. cha. ſerueth to this en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / to teach that the great miſeries / and calamities / which the Iues ſuffred by the force / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oppreſſion of Nabuchodonoſor / and the Babiloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans / came not vpon them by chaunce / but by the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinance / and prouidence of God / ſo this viſion / which. S. Ioan moſt liuely ſetteth before vs / ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in like maner / that the decaie / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ruine the afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions / and perſequutions of the churche in this la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter time / and what ſo euer is don in the world b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Antichriſt / and his membres / is not toſſed at auen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture by hap / but gouerned by the hand / and certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne prouidence of God. And it is right neceſſarie for vs to know / that fortune and chaunce rule nor th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> roſt in mennes matters / rufflinge and tombling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> al thinges confuſedly / as Epicures diſciples thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / but that god is the orderer / diſpoſer / and goue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of al the thinges that be don in the world. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is not poſſible for vs to quiete our ſelues / whan we conſidre the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / and great proſperitee / and lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kie ſucceſſe of falſe teachers / of Chriſtes ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed enemies / of moſt vngodlie cruel / barbarous / and wicked men / onles we be ſtaied with this / tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> god ruleth / ordreth / and gouerneth al together / S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore that there ſhalbe an ende of the raginge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5636:4"/> tyrannous perſequutors / and that the gouerner of al / ſhal turne al to the iuſt deſtruction / of the wicked to the conforte of his choſen / and to the adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his awne glorie. Againe if we loke vpon our pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate ſtate / and cal to compte our frailtie, and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie / the manifold diſeaſes / and miſeries whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to wear ſubiecte / what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue / or what ende of morninge and ſorow / if we be not perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / that Goddes prouid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce reacheth vnto vs / and ordreth al that commeth vpon vs / not as ſemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs / but as he knoweth to be beſt for vs.</p>
               <p>But here I muſt warne you of two notable fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. One is of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which whan they heare vs ſaie / that al thinges comme to paſſe / by goddes prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / thincke / and affirme that we teache / that god is the autor of al the ſinful actes / that ar don in the world. Which is moſt falſe / moſt horrible / and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtable / <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther to be ſpoken / or thought. For it is as impoſſible for god / who is al together good / to be the autor of evil / as it is impoſſible for him / to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of his godhead / and to be no more god. We ſaie than conſtantly / and with al vehementie of minde / that God is the outer of no euil / and we meane it not ſo / that bycauſe god worcketh it / therefore it is good / though of it ſelfe it be euil / but we meane / that he is in dede the propre worcker / and cauſe of no euil / that euil / and ſinne ſpringe not from him / but from the diuel / and from vs / and that he is ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply
<pb facs="tcp:5636:4"/>
/ and merely the autor / and worcker of good thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges only / both whan he worcketh by him ſelfe / and whan he worcketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and in vs. And yet we ſaye that nothinge commeth to paſſe without him / and that he ordreth / diſpoſeth / te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h / and bringeth forth to light / al the euil actes that ar do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. But it is one thinge to vttre / to bringe forth / to diſpoſe / and ordre mennes euils / and it is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinge to worcke / and to cauſe euils in men.</p>
               <p>It is one thinge to make an inſtrument euil / and it is another thinge to vſe an euil inſtrument / beinge alreadie ſo made by another. To make an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euil / is euil / to vſe an euil inſtrument / is not euil ſimply / yea to vſe an euil inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to good endes / is good. Satan / and our awne wil / hathe made vs al euil inſtrumentes. God though we be now ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de il inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / vſeth vs wel. Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and our aw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne wil hath wrought / and cauſed wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dnes in vs al. God moderateth / repreſſeth / ſtirreth vp / and bringeth forth the euil / that Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; we haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in our ſelues / ſo that we vttre no parte of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil that is in vs / by Satans enuie / and our awne faute and follie / but where and whan it pleaſeth god the gouernor of the vniuerſal world. And thus I truſt, it is not harde to perceaue, that though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge comme to paſſe beſides Goddes prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / yet he is not the autor / and worcker / and verie cauſe of anie maner of euil / and ſinful acte. For he
<pb facs="tcp:5636:5"/> worcketh not euil in our hertes / but findinge euil there alreadie wrought / he ether ſtoppeth / and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the ſame / or ſtirreth it vp / and bringeth it forth / and maketh it knowen to the world / as he knoweth to make moſt for his glorie / &amp; for the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite of his choſen.</p>
               <p>Thother faute is of them / which acknowlege God to be the ruler / and gouerner of al thinges / and yet they finde faulte in his gouernment. For they aſke / why God prouided not other wiſe in the beginninge / than that Satan ſhuld bringe man to tranſgreſſion / why he ſtopped not his enterpriſe at the firſt / for ſo ſhuld there haue ben no euil in the world or why now he doeth not deſtroie al wicked men / al the aduerſaries of his ſonne at once / or ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke them al good men that we might liue a quiete / happie / and pleaſant life without miſerie / without murmuringe / without filthines of manners in al puritie / and godlines / where as now the world is ful of calamities / ful of pleges / ful of vile actes / ful of falſe doctrine / idolatrie / and ſuperſtition / an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſte preuaili<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge euerie where / makinge hauocke / beatinge doune / and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pinge vndre his fete al that is good / and godlie. Theſe men wold haue God / and his doinges ſubiecte to theyr iudgementes ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / and what ſo euer they cannot comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with theyr wittes / they can find no reaſon nor goodnes in it. They wil not make theyr iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes agree to
<pb facs="tcp:5636:5"/> Goddes doinges / but they wil haue God to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke his doinges agree to theyr iudgementes. But what if God wil not do them that honor / vntil they can ſhew them ſelues / as wiſe / as he is.</p>
               <p>Shal a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ninge artificer alter his worcke / bicau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe a foliſh vnſkilful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeme to himſelfe to finde a faute in it. No man in this life can attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to a ful reaſon of Goddes doinges. But we ſhal ſee in this part off the ſcripture / that they which ar now departed out of this life / and liue in a better life / find that God hath don al thinges moſt wiſely / iuſtly / &amp; ordredly / whereunto thei cold not fully attayne / whyle they liued in this world. But though I ſaie / that men in this life can not attaine to a ful knowlege / and reaſon of al goddes doinges / yet I denie not / but that thei haue ſome knowlege / and ſe ſome reaſon in his doinges. For touchinge the firſt queſtion / if god had hindred Satans entrepriſe / at the beginnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Satans wickednes / and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes frailtie / than goddes righteouſnes in puniſhinge ſinne / and his moſt wonderful goodnes in the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed before / and now perfirmed incarnation of his ſonne / cold neuer haue ben knowen. And tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the ſeconde queſtion / that he now ſuffreth Antichriſt to make ſuch an hurley burley / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in the world / therein his wiſedom / and righteouſnes appereth plainly / in bringing to
<pb facs="tcp:5636:6"/> light the outragious nawghtines of men / and in ſtrikinge the reprobate with deſerued blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. His mercie alſo and goodnes ſhineth forth / moſt clearely in ſauing / and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeruing his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen / in the middeſt of al errors / and blindnes / in in the middeſt of al ſtomblinge blockes / and dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which is no leſſe to be meruailed at / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the noble childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Hebru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vnhur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / in the hote burninge ouen. But now that I haue ſhewed you the ende of this viſion, with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me aunſweres to the obiections of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie or vnlerned / I wil breifely ſhew you the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / and ſo comme to a more particular conſidera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the texte. This is the viſion in ſumme. In heauen there appeareth a throne of imperial maieſtie. Vpon this throne there ſitteth one hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge a boke in his right hand ſealed with .7. ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. A lambe as it were ſlaine / is aſſociated / and ioigned with him / that ſitteth vpon the throne / which receueth the boke / and openeth the ſeales thereof. Out of this throne there procedeth a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenfolde ſpirite / which ſheweth forth his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreful power. Before the throne there is a glaſſie ſea cleare / and chryſtalline. The throne leaneth vpon .4. beaſtes / which haue eyes / and winges. Then a grene rainebow like an emrode co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſeth the throne / as it were a garlande. In a circle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the throne be .24. ſeates / and in them ſitte
<pb facs="tcp:5636:6"/> 24. elders crouned / and clothed in white garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. This is the ſumme of the viſion / which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth a more particular declaration. But firſt we muſt ſpeake ſome what of thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / which S. Ioan ſetteth before this viſion / which he ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly painteth forth. Thus he ſpeaketh befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</p>
               <p>AFTER theſe thinges I ſaw) S. Io. ſaw other viſions before / declaringe to him / how the Lord Ieſus raigneth in his churche / and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it / what preceptes / what exhortations / what chaſtiſementes he vſeth in it / and againe what the dutie of the church is towardes hir lord / and kinge. Al which thinges ar diſcribed in in the former chapitres.</p>
               <p>I ſaw) That is a viſion appeared vnto me.</p>
               <p>AND behold a dore was opened in heauen) Where a dore ſtandeth open / men maie entre in. So by this ſpeech. S. Io. ſignifieth / that he was admitted in to the contemplation of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Wherein the great goodnes of God is ſette before vs / who vouchſafeth to open the dore of his ſecrete cloſette to a mortal man. But ſee the ſame goodnes yet more declared. For manie ſee a Kinges priuie chamber dore ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and yet ar aferd to entre in. Such feare and baſhefulnes might happen to. S. Ioan / and therefore God confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him / and maketh him bold. For he ſaieth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:7"/>
               <p>AND the firſt voice that I heard was as it had ben of a tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe ſpeaking with me / and ſaiyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / comme vp hither) Henrie Bullinger a verie godlie / and lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / thinketh that this voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / was the voice of Chriſt / which I like wel. If you wil take it rather for the voice of an angel / I wil not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tende therein / ſo that you vndreſtand / that the angel ſpake vnto Io. after this ſorte / by the appointement of Chriſt. For whether the lord ſhew his goodnes to vs by hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe / or by his cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atures / it is al one. Al procedeth from him / and therefore he is only to be glorified. The voice was like the ſound of a trompe / whereby is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified that it was no fainte thinge / but mightie in worcking / and able to take awaie al feare / and to perſuade thoroughly.</p>
               <p>COMME vp hither) The nature of erth is / to fal to the erth / and not to riſe vpwarde.</p>
               <p>We ſhuld neuer riſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the erth / onles God did cal vs / and raiſe vs vp. But if we wil conſidre god / and his worckes / we muſt aſcende / we muſt flie vp far aboue the erth / far aboue our fleſh / and our awne reaſon to. That Bullinger ſaieth that we muſt purge our ſelues from erthie affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions / if we wil beholde heauenlie thinges / it is a verie good ſenſe alſo.</p>
               <p>AND j wil ſhew the what ſhal be don here after) That god vouchſafeth to make men priuie to his doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / it is a goodnes neuer thought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5636:7"/> neuer comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded enough. Which thinge he ſhal ſone perceue / that conſidereth what god is / and what we ar / his exceding great maieſtie / &amp; our exceding great vilenes. Which matter I wil not now enlarge / but leaue to your conſideration.</p>
               <p>This wold be wel noted that he ſaieth / that he wil ſhew him thinges that muſt be don after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For ſome expoune the thinges that are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken hereafter / partly of thinges do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vndre the old teſtament / and partly of thinges don vndre the new. Which muſt nedes be an error / and lead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to wronge opinions / makinge them beginne at a wronge ende / ſith he ſaieth plainly / that he wil ſhew thinges to be don / after the tyme that he ſpake with him / and not thinges don before.</p>
               <p>AND ſtreight waie I was in the ſpirite) I was ſo occupied and deteined altogether in the ſpirite / as if I had / had no bodie / as though I had forgotten al bodilie / and erthlie thinges.</p>
               <p>Or the ſpirite of god came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me / and poſſeſſed me / or as Bullinger writeth I was in a ſpiritual contemplation / and rapte in ſpirite. That he ſaieth ſtreight waie / he ſheweth the might / and efficacie of the voice / that ſpake vnto him.</p>
               <p>AND beholde a throne was ſette in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) Goddes throne is often ſpoken of / and deſcribed in the ſcripture. For Eſaie ſaieth in the .6. cha. that he ſaw god ſittinge vpon a throne high / and
<pb facs="tcp:5636:8"/> aduanced / and his traine filled the temple &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the firſt cha. of his prophetie Ezechiel ſaieth / that he ſaw in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as it were a ſaphir / and the likenes of a throne. And he repeteth the ſame in the .10. cha. Daniel in the .7. cha. ſheweth that he ſaw goddes throne gliſteringe like fier / and the wheles of it ſent forth fierie flammes. But god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des throne is no where deſcribed ſo fully / ſo liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / and with ſo conninge and pleaſant wordes / as in this place. What this throne ſignifieth / we maie eaſely gather out of the wordes of kinge Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid / for thus he ſingeth in the .9. pſal. God ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maine for euer / he hath made readie his throne to iudgement. And he ſhal iudge the world in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes / and decide the peoples matters with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite. So than we vnderſtand by the throne god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des imperial gouernment / and his iudiciarie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. This throne is not in erth / but in heauen. For god <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uleth not after anie erthlie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner / but after an heauenlie maner. Nether is his iudgement and gouernment corruptible / and ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iecte to an ende / but as Dauid ſaieth / he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a iudge / a ruler / and gouerner for euer. For in the hebrue tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / to iudge ſignifieth to ordre / to rule / and gouerne.</p>
               <p>AND vpon the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at there was one ſitting) You know that it is god / &amp; his ſon / that ſitteth vpon this throne .j. adminiſtreth / ruleth / and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth
<pb facs="tcp:5636:8"/> al thinges.</p>
               <p>AND he that ſate was in ſight like a iaſpis / and a ſardine ſtone) By the colors of two preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones the nature of God is ſome wiſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed to ſaint Io. and to vs. Plinie writeth that a iaſpis is a grene ſtone / which is a freſh / and a pleaſant color / and the color of manie thinges that ar luſtie / and liuelie. And therefore writers vnderſtand thereby goddes perpetual continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance / his incorruptible / and immortal nature / as Dauid ſaieth / thy yeres ſhal not be ended. And not only that he is the euer liuinge God / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth euer in life him ſelfe / but alſo that he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life to al other liuinge creatures / and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them in grene / and luſtie freſhnes. A ſardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne hath a fierie color / and maie expreſſe vnto vs goddes ſore iudgement / and vengeance vpon vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>repentant ſinners.</p>
               <p>And a raine bow was aboute the throne like in ſight to an emrode) It is meruailous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable to vs / that goddes throne is compaſſed aboute with the raine bow. For the raine bow is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of goddes perpetual mercie / and of his moſt gratious couen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made with vs. Who might abi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the iuſtice / and ſeueritee of goddes throne / if it were not compaſſed with mercie? For as Dauid ſaieth / if god wold obſerue iniquites / accordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to his righteouſnes / who ſhuld ſtand? But he
<pb facs="tcp:5636:9"/> hath ſet his raine bow / and ſacrament of mercie ſo round aboute his throne / that his eyes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer be of from it. He ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turne his ſight no waie / but he muſt ſee it. And therefore now it is not to vs a terrible / and dradful throne / but as. S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le calleth it / a throne of grace / whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to we maie approche with boldnes / and find readie helpe.</p>
               <p>The color of this raine bow was like the color of an emrode / which is the moſt freſch / &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant color / that anie ſtone hath. For in dede there is nothinge ſo delectable / and pleaſant to vs / as goddes couenant of grace / and mercie. And this couenant is euer grene / and endureth euer to the behofe of the choſen.</p>
               <p>AND aboute the throne were .24. thrones &amp;) That the .24. elders ſat vpon thrones / fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the greke worde is al one here / and whan menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made of goddes throne / and that thei were crouned / I thincke in dede that by them we muſt vndreſtand with Bullinger / the companie of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſainctes departed out of this world / &amp; now raigninge and triumphinge with the lord Ieſus in heauen. And I thincke that an alluſion is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / and a regarde had to the kinges of this world which haue their counſellers / and noble men ſit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge aboute them. For the ſcripture deſcribeth heauenlie matters to vs / by ſuch thinges as ar in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vs. Bullinger noteth that .24. is made
<pb facs="tcp:5636:9"/> of .12. And that the .12 Patriarches ſignifie at Iſrael / and the old church before the incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt. And the chriſtiane church was planted by .12. Apoſtles / ſo that the nombre of 12. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the hole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the new people. And after this ſorte .24. ſignifie the hole triumphant church conſiſtinge of Iues and ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. Theſe .24. ar apparelled with white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. For Chriſt hath purged them / &amp; made them faire / and clothed them with his awne puritee / and righteouſnes. They ar crouned / for they ouercame Satan / and his helliſch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie / while they liued in this world. And now they raigne as kinges with Chriſt the lord in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glorie. That they ſitte / Bullinger ſaieth it is not ment / that they be iudges / but thei ar ſaid to ſitte / bicauſe thei reſt from theyr labors / and now haue quiete affections / and be far from trobleſome paſſions of mind.</p>
               <p>Howbeit I ſee not, why mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be made of thrones, if we ſhal not vndreſtand, that they ſit as iudges. Not that we meane, that they iudge in ſtede of Chriſt, but we meane, that thei iudge with him, that is to ſaie, alow his iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, thinckinge the ſame thinge in euerie matter, that he doeth, and reioiſing in his doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For the lord hath aduanced them, to this dignitee, as to ſitte with him in iudgement.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:10"/>
               <p>For he hath made al his thinges commune to his ſainctes. His iudgementes, he hath made theyr iudgementes, his kingdom, their kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his raigninge, their raigninge, and ſo forth.</p>
               <p>Now by this deſcription of the thrones, golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crounes, goodlie garmentes of the ſainctes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this life, we maie vndreſtand the greate glorie, and felicitee, that thei liue in.</p>
               <p>Which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſhuld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte vs in theſe our afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, and miſeries, that we faint not, or be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, knowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that goddes ſaictes paſſed by the ſame, &amp; now triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phe in perpetual ioie. The old heathen, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of great wittes, taught the youthe of their tyme, that vertue dwelleth vpon the toppe of an high hille and that the waie to the hil toppe is verie rough, laborſom, &amp; tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but whan a man is once comme to the top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, he ſhal find a goodlie plaine, goodlie grene medowes, and al maner of pleaſures. We know, taught by a more certaine ſcole maſter, that the waie to heauen is verie ſtraite, and that thorough manie afflictions, we muſt entre in to goddes kingdom. But whan we be once co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thither, it can nether be ſpoken nor thought, what ioie, what pleaſure, what felicitee we ſhal finde there. Wherefore ſith the ende of thoſe thinges, whereunto we ar called, bringeth ſo great glorie, and ſo great a ſea of al pleaſures, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5636:10"/> ioies, we ought not to be diſmaide, bycauſe of the difficulties, &amp; irckſome tediouſnes, that we finde by the waie. For we ſhal ſone paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough them. We can not longe ſticke in them. For what is longe in this life? Let vs therefore gird vp the loines of our minde, as. S. Petre ſpeaketh, and preſſe forward to the price of the ſupernal callinge of god, in Chriſt Ieſu. Let vs with patience runne out the race, that we ar ſet in, faſteni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge our eyes vpon the autor, &amp; finiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her of our faith, who for the ioie, that was ſet before him, ſuſtained, and deſpiſed the ſhame of the croſſe, and now is ſit doune vpon the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous throne of God, and wil leade vs the ſame waie, to like honor, glorie, and dignite. Vnto god therefore, who hath ſanctified our trauailes, our croſſe, and our miſeries, and made the iſſue / &amp; end ſo happie. and bliſful, be al glorie, and honor for euer. Amen.</p>
               <p>The nexte ſondrie after this lecture, one of the companie ſemed by circumſtances to impro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſome parte thereof. But whan we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred together, we fully agreed. Where vpon I vttered this declaration folowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reading">
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:11"/>
               <head>¶ The ſeconde readinge.</head>
               <p>It is verie certaine, that not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vnbrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wanton wittes of vngodlie, wild, fanatical, arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and proud ſpirites, ſporte them ſelues in mockinge of goddes proui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but alſo that the weake, vnlerned, &amp; vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed mindes of ſome g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dlie folke, ar trobled with this, that where as thei heare, &amp; be taught by the holie ſcripture, that god is the ruler, and gouerner / of the hole world / yet thei ſee, that the deſpicers, and contemners of god, &amp; godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hateth, and abhorreth, proſper in the world, they ſee that the godlie, whom god lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth, ar oppreſſed, &amp; vily entreated, thei ſee that lies falſhod, violence, tyrannie, falſe and fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tike opinions, idolatrie, and ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, raigne eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where, and truth, righteouſnes, vertue, &amp; al honeſtie, is troden vndre fote, and lieth woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, maimed, &amp; mangled in the mire of the ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Yea not only the weake ar offended here with but alſo ſome farther growen, and more exerciſed, and endued with greater knowlege, beginne to ſlagger, and to doubte, whether the world be gouerned by goddes prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther al thinges be tombled, and toſſed by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, whan they ſee in how great welt hand felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the vngodlie liue, and how the godlie wraſtle
<pb facs="tcp:5636:11"/> &amp; tugge continually, with al maner of miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and calamities. For Aſaph confeſſeth that his fete were al moſt ouerturned, and his ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes ſlidden, whan he ſaw the peace .i. the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritee of the vngodlie. He was ſo nigh a fal that he was al moſt comme to this, to ſaie, I haue plainly clenſed my herte in vaine, vntil he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in to goddes holie places, conſidered more depely, his prouidence, and ſo perced farther, &amp; vndreſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de the ende of the vngodlie, how God had ſett them in a ſlipperie place, to giue them a more ſhameful fal. And therefore, that is to be noted, he confeſſeth, that before god had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him, in to a farther vndreſtanding of his prouidence, while he folowed his awne witie in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideringe the affaires, &amp; happes of the world, he was a verie beaſte before god. Ieremie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, though he acknowlege, that the world is go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerned by goddes prouidence, yet he can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehende, by his witte, but that thinges might be don better. For thus he ſaieth. Thou art iuſt lord, if I ſhuld contende with the. By theſe wordes it appeareth, that he acknowlegeth god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des prouidence, in gouerninge the world. For why ſhuld he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine to god, aboute thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, where with god ſhuld haue no thinge to do if the world were not gouerned by him? Or why ſhuld he acknowlege god to be iuſt in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:5636:12"/> thinges, wherein he is offended, and trobled, if thei were not ordred by him. For theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, thou art iuſt lord / if I ſhuld contende with the, ſignifie aſmuche, as if he ſhuld ſaie, I know lord, that al thinges ar gouerned by the, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to paſſe by thy prouidence, &amp; that thou haſt a iuſt reaſon in al thy doinges, but I can not ſee it in manie thinges, and namely in the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the vngodlie. For it foloweth, yet I wil ſpeake iudgementes with the that is, yet me thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth ſome thinges go not right. Why is the waie of the vngodlie proſperous, why be they happye, and liue in al welth, &amp; ioilitie, that tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe tranſgreſſion, that is, which be extreme, and exceding great tranſgreſſors of thy lawes? This is the thinge, that trobleth the Prophete, that ſemeth not right. For it ſemeth to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes reaſon iuſter, that god ſhuld adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per his frendes, and faithful ſeruantes, and nat ſuch, as deſpice him and his. But it is wel, that he acknowlegeth that god is iuſt. For the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby he confeſſeth, that there maie be ſome what more in the matter, thou he cold attaine vnto.</p>
               <p>And yet he is angrie with him ſelfe, that he cold not perceaue the reaſon of it. If this happened to ſo notable men, to men furniſched with ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent graces of god, to men ſo much exerciſed in ſpiritual matters, it is more certaine, that
<pb facs="tcp:5636:12"/> weake, and vnpractiſed mindes, wold be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, trobled &amp; amaſed with this, that antichriſt ſhuld oppreſſe goddes miniſters, ouerthrow, &amp; al moſt quenche out the goſpel of Chriſt, &amp; al tru doctrine, ſette vp, and blaſe abrode falſe religion, thorough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut al the world, and triumphe in his miſcheife, not a few daies, but manie hundred ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res. Bycauſe this muſt nedes be verie offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to manie, and make them wauer, and doute of goddes prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it pleaſed god to ſhew afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rehand, by other his prophetes, and apoſtles, &amp; by this his faithful ſeruant. S. Ioan, that theſe thinges ſhuld comme to paſſe, that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might know, that they fal not in by chaunce, but be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, and ordred by his wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and fore know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege, and ſo arme them ſelues with patience, in ſuch ouerthwarte iſſues, as they ſome to vs, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideringe that god doeth al thinges moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and wiſely, to his awne glorie, and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theraunce of his choſen. If you wil knew the cauſes, why god hath appointed, and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that antichriſt ſhal riſe, and ſet vp his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and beate doune the tru church, &amp; ſtabliſhe his countrefaite preiſthode, his kingdom of ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelinges, his mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckerie, nonrie, and al his pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, his falſe doctrine, and open beaſtlie errors, ſerch the ſcriptures. And if you find cauſes there expreſſed, ſee that ye reuerence in them goddes
<pb facs="tcp:5636:13"/> wiſedom, and righteouſnes. As in dede ſome be there expreſſed, as I doubte not but you ſhal heare at large, whan our brother ſhal comme to that place in the .2. epiſtle to the Theſſal. If you find not al there expreſſed, or be not ſatiſfied with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that be there expreſſed, crie out with S. Paule. O the depenes of the riches, of the wiſedom, and knowlege of god &amp; But yet there is one thinge more, that trobleth manie wittes now a daies, wherein perchaunce they maie be ſatiſfied, or ſome what quieted, and that is, how it can be, that al thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to paſſe, by goddes wil, and ordinance, &amp; yet manie thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the world be don againſt his worde, and againſt his wil. It is no meruail, if this be hard to vndreſtande. For. S. Auguſtine grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, by a wondreful, &amp; vnſpeakable maner, that, that commeth not to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe beſide goddes wil, that is don againſt his wil. But ye ſhal know, that whan men do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil worckes, concerninge the faute, and vice of their actes, they do that, that is againſt goddes wil, but concerninge the end, and that, that god wil turne theyr euil actes vnto, thei do the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that god wil haue to be don. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. S. Auguſtine ſaieth, verie profoundly, &amp; lernedly. Theſe be the great, wonderful, and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſite worckes of god, that whan mannes, and
<pb facs="tcp:5636:13"/> angels nature had ſinned, that is, had don, not that he wold, but that thei wold, euen by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wil of the creature, whereby that was don, that the creator wold not, he fulfilled that he wold, vſinge wel euen euil thinges, as ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely good him ſelfe, to the damnation of them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he iuſtly fore ordained to puniſhment, and to the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them, whom he mercifully fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reordained to grace. For as touchinge them ſelues, thei did that god wold not, but touchinge the omnipotentie of god, thei cold no waie do it. For euen in this, that thei did againſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wil, goddes wil was don vpon them. By theſe wordes he teacheth that though god ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre mennes nawghtie, and wicked dedes, yet thei comme not to paſſe beſides his wil, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance touching the end and vſe of them. For he wil make mennes nawghtie dedes, ſerue to good endes, and vſes. And therefore the ſame autor ſaieth againe. When in the laſt daie Chriſt ſhal comme to iudge the world, than in the moſt cleare light of wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it ſhal appeare, that now the faith of the godlie hath, how certaine, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable, and moſt effectual goddes wil is, how manie thinges he can do, and wil not, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth nothinge that he can not do, and how tru it is, that is ſounge in the pſal. Our god is in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, he hath don, whatſoeuer he wold, which ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely
<pb facs="tcp:5636:14"/> is not tru, if he wold haue ſome thinges don, and hath not don them. There is not than anie thing don, onles the omnipotent wil haue it don, ether in ſuffringe it to be don, or in doinge it himſelfe. Hitherto. S. Auguſtin.</p>
               <p>And that you maie vndreſtand, that he taketh goddes ſuffringe, for goddes ordinance, though god worcke ſondrie waies, ſome tymes by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſome tymes by his creatures good, &amp; bad, he goeth farther, &amp; ſaieth more ouer. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theri sit to be douted, but that god doeth wel in ſuffring to be don, what ſoeuer is don il.</p>
               <p>For he ſuffreth not this / but by iuſt iudgement. Though than thoſe thinges, that be euil, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thei be euil, be not good, yet it is good, that not only good thinges, but alſo euil thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſhuld be. For if this were not good / that euil thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges alſo ſhuld be / thei ſhuld in no wiſe be ſuffred of the almighty good i. god. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without doubte as eaſie as it is, to do what he wil, ſo eaſie is it, not to ſuffre, that he wil not to be don. Out of theſe wordes we lerne, that the diuine man. S. Auguſt. vndreſtode, that al the thinges in the world comme to paſſe by the ordinance of god, and that goddes wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſuch, that he ſaw it good / that euil thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ſhuld be, and his power ſuch: that he cold turne thoſe euils to good. Now leſt anie man ſhuld thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:5636:14"/> here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that god is the autor of euil, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that there is ſome thinge in mennes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, not by goddes propre worckinge, but by his ordinance / to a certaine end, and by the propre worckinge in dede of Satan, and by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nawghtines. For god wrought not nawgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines in Adams herte firſt, but ordained, that Satan moued with his awne malice ſhuld tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Adam to euil, &amp; worcke nawghtines in him thorough Adams awne faute. And that nawgh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tines al Adams ofſpringe, &amp; poſterite draw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. Now than after this ſorte al men ar made / euil and ful of nawghtie deſires. God the gouernor of the world wil haue this nawgh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tines / that lurcketh in mennes hertes / to be bewraied, and brought forth to light, whereby his awne wiſedom, righteouſnes, and mercie maie be declared. So than he ordaineth that this man ſhal vttre in acte the lecherous deſires that lie hidden in his herte, this his theuiſhe, this his murtherous minde. And thus he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth al mennes euil actes, ſo that no thinge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe beſide his ordinance, but he is not the autor, and propre worcker of the euil, that is in mennes hertes. If he did worcke, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe an adulterous mind in a man, whoſe mind was pure, and innocent before, and than moued him to vttre the ſame in acte, and dede, he ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:5636:15"/> be the autor of euil. But if he worcke not that adulterous mind, but findeth the mind corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and defiled by Satan, and by the perſon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and than ordaineth where, and whan, &amp; to what endes the ſame ſhalbe made open to the world, he is not the autor, and worcker, but the orderer, and diſpoſer of euil. And in this matter thus vndreſtanded, you ſhal know that al we, whom it hath pleaſed god to appointe to treate his word in this place, do agree. For he that ſaid, that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> goddes wil, that Adam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld ſinne, in it not ſimply &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> waie / that it was not goddes wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, but he ment, that tou hinge the ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fulnes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams acte, it was not goddes wil, that he ſhuld ſinne, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inge the end, and that, that god wold turne Adam ſinful acre vnto, he graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that it was goddes wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne. This much I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hought good to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, bicauſe S. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annes viſion leadeth vs to a conſideration of goddes prouidence, and or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dringe of al thinges / that happen to the church in this later tyme: wherein we can not walke ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fely, o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>les we know the thinges, that I haue told you. Now to the texte.</p>
               <p>And there proceded out of the throne light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges and tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and voices, and .7. lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of fier burninge before the throne which he
<pb facs="tcp:5636:15"/> the .7. ſpirites of god) Theſe wordes in my opinion teach that al the thinges that ar don in the world procede out of goddes iudgement, &amp; be the effectes of his ſpirite. Whan the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of goddes choſen be illuminated, &amp; light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whan the wicked ar fraied / &amp; horribly ſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with goddes threates, as it were with light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goddes preachers tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre againſt the corrupte maners of the world, whan thei ſend forth the ſwete voices of the goſpel, whan they exhorte and comforte, breifely whan thei ſhew anie grace and vertue, al this procedeth out of godd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s throne, out of goddes iudgement, and theſe be the mighty worckes of his ſpirite.</p>
               <p>Whereby the prouidence of god is certainly ſet before vs in gouerninge the world. For by theſe ſpecial efficies, we muſt vnderſtande the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r if anie parte of the world, and men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes doinges, be gouerned by goddes prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, than al is gouerned by the ſame, ſith there is no conuenience, nor reaſon why he ſhuld medle with parte, and not with al. For it agreeth nether with his goodnes / nor with his power, that he ſhuld leaue anie thing vnloked to, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouerned. And therefore the ſcripture aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the leſt, and moſt conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tible worckes that be don in the world to goddes prouidence, as in hewinge of wood, the fallinge of an axe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:5636:16"/> helue, whereby a man is ſlaine. And in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis tabernacle not only the golden table, the gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den cherubs, the golden arke, were made by god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des appointement, but alſo the gredirons, the diſches, the ſpones, and the ſnuffers, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther baſe thinges. S. Io. reciteth the cheife worckes of god, thondringes, lightninges, and voices, to giue vs a light to ſee al the reſt, and to make a waie to entre farther.</p>
               <p>And ſeuen lampes burninge) By theſe .7. lampes I vndreſtand, the holie goſt, and his ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drie giftes, and graces, which burne, ar quicke, liuelie, and buſie in worcking, giue light, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to goddes choſen without ceaſing. This is Moſeis golden candleſticke, with ſeuen can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles burninge continually.</p>
               <p>Which be the .7. ſpirites of god) The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen lampes be, that is ſignifie, &amp; repreſent the ſeuen ſpirites of god. But how is it, that he attributeth to god .7. ſpirites. For we know, that god hath but one ſpirite, and that ſpirite ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be diuided, and ſondred in to partes.</p>
               <p>G ddes one ſpirite is called ſeuen ſpirites, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is furniſhed with, ſeuen, that is / with ſondrie and innumerable graces. For ſeuen in the ſcripture is a perfecte no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fulnes. So goddes ſeuen ſpirites, is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much to ſaie, as goddes ſeuenfold ſpirite, that is
<pb facs="tcp:5636:16"/> goddes ſpirite ful of al good giftes procedeth from goddes throne .i. is ſent in to mennes her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / and worcketh ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndrie effectes in them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to goddes iudgement.</p>
               <p>And in the ſight of the throne there was a glaſſie ſea like Chryſtal) The ſea is varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / and vnſtable / ſome tymes caume / &amp; quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / ſome tymes trobleſome and raging / and therefore the world is expreſſed by it in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture / wherein there is much toſſing and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiling / great vnſtablenes / manie wondreful chaunges / and turnes. This ſea is glaſſie.</p>
               <p>Glaſſe is alſo verie britle / and maie ſignifie the frailtie of the world. But bycauſe the ſea is afterward likened to chryſtal / and that both glaſſe / and chryſtal excelle in clearnes / I thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that the ſea is ſaid to be glaſſie / and chriſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line / bycauſe that al thinges / that ar do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world / ar open to goddes eyes. For as in chriſtal there is not a thinge ſo litle, but that it maie be ſeen / ſo there is no thinge do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world ſo ſmal / as that it can eſcape Goddes ſight and knowlege. This ſea is before the throne / that is / ſubiecte to goddes iudgement, rule / and gouernment. And therefore fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / and chaunce haue no place therein. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderately / and atauenture.</p>
               <p>Men do not what they liſt / but their doinges
<pb facs="tcp:5636:17"/> ar ſubiecte to Goddes throne. The Medes / and Perſians did not what they liſted / nor put on weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr awne deuiſe without god againſt the Babilonians / but as we haue in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaie / the lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded his ſanctified .i. who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had prepared / and he called his ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iant ſoldiars / to exequute his wrath. Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib the kinge of the Aſſirians did not what he liſted againſt the people of Ieruſalem. For god ſaide / that he wold put an hooke in his noſtrels / and a bridle in his lippes / and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge him backe / by the waie / that he came.</p>
               <p>Yea what ſoeuer he did againſt Ieruſalem / he did by goddes appointment. For thus ſaieth god in the .19. of Eſai. O Aſſur / the rod of my furie / and the ſtaffe of my wrath. I wil ſend him to an hypocrital people / I wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund him agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the people of my indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſpoiles &amp;c. Nabuchodonoſor did not / what he liſted / nor roſe of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe without god / againſt Sion. For god ſaieth in the .29. of Eſa. to Dauids citie. I wil beſege the / and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultee the by towres / and raiſe vp heapes of erth / againſt the. And of the kinge of Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / he ſaieth in the .51. of Iere. Thou art my hammer / and weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of warre / I haue by the beaten doune natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and deſtroied kindo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes. I haue by the beaten doune the horſe / and his
<pb facs="tcp:5636:17"/> rider &amp;c. Seinge than that men ar ſubiecte to goddes throne / and do not what they liſt / but be his inſtrumentes ſcourges / hatchettes / and hammers / we ought patiently to ſuſtaine our preſent affliction, and the great miſerie of our countree. And we maie wel conceaue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of conforte, and of better ſtate, conſideringe / that god hath alſo, an hoke in the noſtrelles, &amp; a ſnaffle in in the mouthes euen of the vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful oppreſſors of his ſeruauntes in England / whereby he wil draw them another waye / and reſtraine theyr rage, whan he hath duly plaged the reprobate, &amp; ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly chaſtiſed his choſen.</p>
               <p>Only lette vs remoue the cauſes, of theſe our miſeries, namely lothinge of goddes holie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, boilinge luſtes, idle wantonnes, and greedie deſires of wordlie thinges, &amp; we ſhal ſee ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pharao, and his furious armie drouned in the red ſea. And we that haue longe ſounge morneful ſonges, ſhal chaunge our tunes, and ſinge another while ioifully with Moſes, and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riam. The lord is our ſtrength, and our praiſe, &amp; he his our ſaluation, this is our god, and we wil magnifie him, our fathers god, and we wil aduance him. For this lette vs praie, to this lette vs ſaie, Amen, amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:18"/>
               <p>¶ After this lecture, it pleaſed the partie ſpoken of before, to make certayne argumentes againſt mine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereunto here foloweth the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reading">
               <head>¶ The third reading.</head>
               <p>My conſcience beareth me witnes, that thorough goddes grace, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I haue taught you the truth in this place, and that I haue ſpoken reuerently of god, and his worckes. I am charged in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with vnreuerent ſpeech. But alas, what ſhuld moue me to ſpeake vnreuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who made me, whan I was nothing, who ſaued me, whan I was loſt, who reſtored me to life whan I was ded, who quited me, whan I was to be damned, who raiſed me vp to heauen, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I was to be caſt in to hel / who hath fed m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from my cradle, and than moſt plentiouſly, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I was an orphane, who alſo I am certaine, hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deliuered me out of manie daungers, thauoi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance whereof to procure, I had nether coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel, nor purpoſe, nor thought, in whom no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5636:18"/> being chaſed out of my countree, and baniſhed from mine acquaintaunce, &amp; knowen frendes, I finde ſwete comforte, and great plentie of ioi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es / euen in the middeſt of teares. But the maner of my ſpeaking foundeth vnreuerently / though in my mind / I maie thincke reuerently.</p>
               <p>If this be an vnreuerent ſpeech, to ſaie, that it was goddes wil, and ordinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, than this is an vnreuerent ſpeech / to ſaie, that it was goddes wil, and ordinance / that the Iues ſhuld crucifie Chriſt, and that Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephes brethern ſhuld ſel him in to Aegypte.</p>
               <p>But the holie goſt ſaieth / by the mouth of his holie Apoſtles / and primitiue church, that the Iues and the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles came together to do, what ſoeuer goddes hand, &amp; purpoſe, had ordained to be don. And the ſame holie goſt ſaieth by the mouth of the right vertuous, and holie man Ioſeph, you ſent me not hither, but god.</p>
               <p>Howbeit you muſt know, that whan we ſaie, that it was goddes wil, and ordinance, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſhuld ſinne, the meaninge is not, that god delighted in Adams ſinne, or that god alowed Adams ſinne, or that god was the propre cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, or propre worcker of Adams ſinne / but the meaning is, that it was goddes wil, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſhuld ſinne, thorough Satans enuie / and Adams awne faulte, not for the ſinnes ſake / or
<pb facs="tcp:5636:19"/> in reſpecte of the ſinne, but for the end that he wold turne the ſinne vnto. And that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le matter, that I haue taught you herein is true I haue a ſure ground. For the ſcripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth plainly, that al the thinges, that ar don in the world, ar gouerned by goddes wil. The teſtimonie of Salomon, is plaine, that God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th wrought al thinges for him ſelfe, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vngodlie, to an euil daie. And. S. Paule ſpeaking of goddes bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding, and reiecting of the Iues, and receauing of the gentiles to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, pronounceth, that al thinges ar of him / by him, and into him. Ieremie repeouing the furious madnes of them, that denied god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des prouidence in his tyme, maketh this dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, with a ſtomake. Who is he, that ſaieth, a thing is don, and god commaunded it not, that is to ſaie, ordained it not? The ſame Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, whan the king of Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purpoſed to inua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the Moabites, and being now in his ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naie, chaunged his purpoſe, and came againſt Ieruſalem, crieth out. I know, lord, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes way is not his awne, nether is it of man / to gouerne, and to directe his awne ſteppes.</p>
               <p>And therefore Salomon ſaieth alſo, that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſteppes ar guided of god. And to tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h vs certainly, that nothinge commeth to paſſe by chaunce, and to remoue al matter of doubtinge
<pb facs="tcp:5636:19"/> in this queſtion, the ſame Salomon teacheth / that thoſe thinges, wherein hap ſemeth moſt to haue place, procede out of the iudgdme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god.</p>
               <p>Lottes, ſaieth he, ar caſt in to the lappe, but the hole iudgement is from Iehoua. How eloquently, and how diligently, is this matter beaten in to mennes heades, in the propheties of Eſaie? Where god, after that he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he wold raiſe vp king Cyrus, from the eaſt, to beate dounne Babilon, and to conquere manie nations, to the confuſion of al Epicures babling bande, aſketh this queſtion. Who hath wrought, and don theſe thinges? And aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth thereto himſelfe. I Iehoua the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſt, and with the laſt, ani hu, I am he. And in the 45. cha. I the lorde, and there is no more, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming light, and cauſing darcknes / making pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, and cauſing euil, that is, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re I Ieho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua do al theſe thinges. Breifely al the places of the ſcripture, that teach, that god is the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and gouernor of the world / teach that al thinges comme to paſſe by his wil, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. But this truth hath had aduerſaries in al ages. For to goe no higher. S. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, though he haue ſome ſentences, that ſome to make with vs, yet he hath one ſentence, that putteth me out of doubte, that he halted, and went to much a wrie in this matter. For
<pb facs="tcp:5636:20"/> writinge vpon one of the prophetes, he ſaieth in mockage, that ſome ar ſo ſtraite mainteiners of goddes prouidence, that they affirme / that god knoweth, how maneflies, &amp; gnattes the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be in the world, which he thincketh to be to baſe a matter, for god to be occupied in. But how vntrue this is, you know, that haue heard the lord Ieſus / who is in goddes boſome, and knoweth al his ſecretes, affirme, that the heares of our heades ar nombred, and that there fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not a litle ſparow vpon the erth, beſide the wil, and ordinance of our heauenlie father.</p>
               <p>Nether maie you thincke, that god knoweth fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and gnattes, and litle ſparowes with irck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom tediouſnes, which is found in man, bicau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of his weacknes. And therefore whan the prophete Eſaie ſpeaketh of goddes prouidence, how he brought forth the armie of heauen, that is to ſaie, the ſtarres, &amp; called euerie one by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſaieth thus Why ſaieſt thou Iacob / my waie is hidden from Iehoua, and my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal paſſe from my god, that is to ſaie, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ordinance extendeth not to me? Doeſt thou not know / that the eternal god Iehoua / who made the vtter moſt partes of the erth, is not werie / nor feleth tediouſnes / or paine, &amp; that his vndreſtanding can not be ſerched out?</p>
               <p>By theſe wordes Hieromes feare, that god
<pb facs="tcp:5636:20"/> ſhuld be ouermuch vnſemely buſied with ſo ſmal thinges, is proued fond, and ſuperfluous.</p>
               <p>Wel, ſuch aduerſaries the truth had than. Howbeit it had alſo as ſtronge maintainers,</p>
               <p>For. S. Auguſtine in the ſame tyme gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and inuincibly defended it, and to this daie he raigneth in it / as a mightie conqueror of al them, that dare hiſſe againſt it. The later ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le men, thought not altogether amiſſe of this matter. For thei ſaie, that al thinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me neceſſarely to paſſe, not by the neceſſitee of natural cauſes, but by the neceſſitee of goddes ordinance, which thei cal neceſſitatem conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie. Some ſophiſters, that folowed afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, delighting them ſelues in choplogike, &amp; in braules, and vaine ſubtilties, labored on tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide to impugne the truth hereof. And in our tyme the popes peare of baſtarde diuines Eckius, and Pigghius haue taken the ſame thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in hand. And not only papiſtes ar buſie herein, but alſo ſome profeſſors of tru religion, ether bicauſe thei be prepoſterouſly feareful, or bicauſe thei haue wanton idle wittes. In this later ordre I compte the hartiehard harti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in England. In the the nombre of the firſt, I put Philippe Melanchthon, who in the beginning, was verie erneſt, and free, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward whan he ſaw, the perue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſite of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb facs="tcp:5636:21"/> world, being a man naturally fearful, he beganne to giue place, and to beare with the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtes in more thinges, than this. Howbeit I thincke ſurely, that he relented not altogether of feare, but partly to winne the weake, whoſe tendre yonge ſtomakes cold not broke ſo hard meate, at the firſt. For he is a right godlie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſtudious to promote ſincere doctrine by al meanes. Melanchih<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n than ſtandeth not plainly with vs, nether ſtandeth he plainly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. For if ye marcke his writinges thoroughly, he impugneth, and beateth doune only this, that god is the autor of ſinne, wher in no man diſſenteth from him, ſaue the mad Manichees in old time, and in our tyme men like to them, the loſt Libertines. I thincke wel, that there be ſome other good men, which to auoide the offenſe of vnlerned tendre eares / forbeare to ſpeake plainly, what thei thincke in this matter. But Zuinglius, and Oecclam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius, two lightes of the worlde, Martinus Lutherus, and Martinus Bucerus, men of in comparable knowlege, and lerninge, Petrus Matyr, and Ioannes Caluinus, of which two the firſt in ſondrie ſciences, and in preſent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines and liuelines of witte excelleth al the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we know in Europe, thother in eloquence, in handſome handlinge, and vndreſtandinge of
<pb facs="tcp:5636:21"/> the ſcripture, is a miracle to al men / euen to the verie papiſtes. Al theſe, by whom god hath moſt wondrefully renued his truth in this later tyme, haue expreſly, plainly, fully, and ſtrongly not only affirmed, but alſo with moſt pithie and ſound reaſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed the thinges, that I haue taught you in this place, &amp; at this preſent reherſe vnto you. Now ſeing I haue ſpoken after the meaning, and maner of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie goſt, and after the vndreſtanding of moſt godlie / and moſt excellently wel lerned men, I truſt you wil not thinke / that I haue ſpoken ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhely, or vnreuerently of god, and his worckes.</p>
               <p>I haue choſen in dede purpoſely, to treate ſuch places amonge you, as touch goddes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence in gouerning the world, partly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte my ſelfe, and you in this woful tyme, and partly to ſhew the inconſiderate wilfulnes of the harriharde hartia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſuch beggerlie doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in England. Now ſome for exerciſe of lerninge / haue ſet them ſelues againſt me in this my trauail, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I nede not to be much aferde, for two cauſes. Firſt becauſe thei brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge not with them bitternes of minde / nor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ether againſt me / or againſt the truth.</p>
               <p>Secondly becauſe they fight with leaden ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. For againſt that / that I ſaid for the tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row mainteinance of goddes prouidence / that
<pb facs="tcp:5636:22"/> it was goddes wil, and ordinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne / they make this fainte reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſinne was iniquitee, but god willeth none ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitee, ergo &amp; I aunſwere, that theſe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians begile them ſelues, in douteful termes.</p>
               <p>For to wil / hath a double ſignification.</p>
               <p>For we maie be ſaid to wil a thinge, whan we alow it, or delight in it. And ſo Dauides worde, lo kaphets, certainly ſignifieth, and ſhuld be thus engliſhed: Thou art not a god, that hath pleaſure in iniquitee. And we maie be ſaid alſo to wil a thinge, whan we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light not in the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge nor alow it, but ordaine it to be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for ſome purpoſe. If theſe men that be our aduerſaries in diſputing / not in meaning / vndreſtand by this world / to wil / that god de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted not in Adams ſin / nor alowed it / ſo ſaie we. And than they fight againſt their awne ſhadowes. But if thei meane / that it was not goddes decree / and ordinance / that Adam ſhuld ſinne, for another purpoſe I mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, than for the reſpecte of ſinne, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſaie / they go aboute to pulle god out of his throne / to ſpoile him of his power / and violently to wreſt out of his handes his office of iudging / and gouerning the world. And thei aſcribe weacknes to god. For they ſo teache, that thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be don whether god wil, or no. The
<pb facs="tcp:5636:22"/> ſecond argument is, that god in forbidding A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam to eate of the frute / doclared his wil to be, that Adam ſhuld not eate thereof. But if god had ben in wil, that Adam ſhuld haue eaten of the frute, that had ben a contrariete in god, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go &amp;c. To this I ſaie ſhortly, that god in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by his commaundment, teſtified to Adam / what his pleaſure was / and what he alowed / and againe what Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s dutie was to do towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des him / but this letted not god to wil, and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cree, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorough his awne fault, ſhuld do the thinge / that god alowed not in it ſelfe / but ordained to be don / for the ende / that he wold turne it vnto. Bycauſe god liked not / nor alowed Adams ſinne, mighte he not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ordaine it to be don for ſome good ende?</p>
               <p>Who hath giuen you ſuch autoritee ouer god to cutte ſhorte his power, that he ſhal do no more than pleaſeth you, or that you can be contente to iudge wel don? Lo how terrible theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons be, which breake in ſhiuers, before they comme to the ſtroke. But now commeth another mightie blow he that doeth the wil of god, pleaſeth god, but Adam in breaking the commaundment of god, pleaſed not god, ergo he did not his wil. I praie you good fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſhuld Adam pleaſe god in doinge goddes wil, and ordinance with a faulte of his awne?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:23"/>
               <p>Senacherth did goddes wil, and ordinance in afflicting the people of Ieruſalem, but by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did it, with a fame of his awne, god plaged him, for doing that, that he teſtifieth, he had appointed him to do. If you can not perceaue, how men maie do Goddes decreed wil / with a fault of their awne / impute it to your ignorance / and want of vndreſtanding / &amp; thincke it not by and by, to be falſe, that your meaſured witte can not comprehende. The nexte argument is like the for ner / God rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded not Adam with benifices / ergo he did not that goddes wil was to be don. I wil make the like reaſon. God rewarded not the Iues with benefites, for crucif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inge of Chriſt, ergo it was not goddes wil / and ordinance / that the Iues ſhuld crucifie Chriſt. But yet the holie goſt ſaieth, that thei did, that goddes hand and purpoſe had foreordained to be don.</p>
               <p>Pigghiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the papiſt frameth the argume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t thus. Adam in ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ninge, and the Iues in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing Chriſtes death, did that god wold, and had ordained before to be don / ergo thei were not to be puniſhed. For right vndreſtanding hereof / ye ſhal know, that god / and wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d men / wil ſome times one thinge, but not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one maner. Adams wil was to ſinne, and goddes wil was, that he ſhuld ſinne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:23"/>
               <p>But Adams wil was to ſinne bycauſe he wold be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qual to god / i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowinge of good, &amp; bad.</p>
               <p>And goddes wil was, that Adam thorough his awne faute ſhuld ſinne / to turne Adams ſinne to good / and to bringe good out of euil.</p>
               <p>The Iues wil was to put Chriſt to death / and goddes wil was / that his ſonne ſhuld die.</p>
               <p>But the Iues wil was / that he ſhuld die, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei wold ſatiſfie their malice, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon him, and godddes wil was / that he ſhuld die, to raunſome his choſen, and ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare h s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>able goodnes. Sainct Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine ſheweth verie handſomely, how god wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ſame thinge / with a good wil / that men wil, which a nawghtie wil. An vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie child <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>h the death of his father / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god wil haue to die. Thei both wil one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, namely the death of the man, but they wil it not, after one ſorte. For the enthriftie ſonne willeth it, to emote his father goodes. God willeth it / to conuete him out of miſerie, if he be one of the choſen / or duly to puniſh him / if he be a reprobate. Is this vnthrifte than wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be rewarded with benifites, bicauſe he wold the ſame thinge that god wold? Naie ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely. For he willed it vniuſtly, to an euil pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and god willed it iuſtly, to a good porpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Boies in ſcoles to practiſe then ſophiſtrie,
<pb facs="tcp:5636:24"/> make the argument, as handſomely, after this ſorte. That wil, that agreeth with goddes wil, is good / the Iues wil agreed with goddes wil, for thei wold that Chriſt ſhuld die, and god alſo wold / that he ſhuld die, ergo their wil was good. To this wiſe men aunſwer, that the Iues wil agreed not with goddes wil, in al cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and in al pointes, and therefore it was not good, but extremely euil. The argument the refore is nawght. For it is deducted ex cauſa non ſufficiente .i. of a cauſe not ſufficient.</p>
               <p>But let vs peruſe more of our aduerſaries rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. God made man to immortalitie, ergo it was not his wil, that he ſhuld ſinne, and die. I aunſwer, that this is not an abſolute ſpeech, god made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to immortalitie, but a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditional. God made man to immortalite, if he wold ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue perſiſted, and continued in the ſtate, that god made him in. Whan Ionas ſaieth / yet .40. daies, and Niniue ſhalbe deſtroied, this ſpeech declareth not goddes ſecrete determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but what ſhuld folow, if thei did not repente.</p>
               <p>God ſaieth to Abimelech, hauing taken to him Abrahams wife. Lo thou ſhalt die for the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom thou haſt taken. This ſemeth an abſolute ſpeech, but in dede it hath a ſecrete condition, which the ſcripture afterwarde expreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth in theſe wordes. Reſtore hir now to hyr
<pb facs="tcp:5636:24"/> huſband, if thou reſtore hir not (ſee the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſed), know that thou ſhalt ſurely die. Yet there remaineth another reaſon, that wold make anie man to quake, if he had nether wit / nor ſparcke of a mannes mind. If you grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tingentiam ſaie thei, than ye affirme, that al thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to paſſe by fatal deſtinee.</p>
               <p>Here firſt I muſt tel you what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tingens is.</p>
               <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tingens is that, which though it be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after ſome certaine ſorte, yet hath of it ſelfe, and of his awne nature, that it might haue ben other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As for exemple / Iulius Ceſar ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peie. There is nothinge in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hereof, but that Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peie might haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me Iulius Ceſar. The legges of the lord Ieſus of theyr awne nature might haue ben bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken. Than we ſaie, that manie thinges of them ſelues, and of their awne nature, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent, but touching goddes wil, and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce there is nothing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tingent in the world, that is to ſaie, nothinge in the world co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, other wiſe than he hath determined, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained. And ſo we ſaie, that Iulius Ceſar muſt nedes ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peie, and that the leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the lord Ieſus cold not be broken by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of goddes ordinance. But ſo we agree with the ſtoikes, that ſaie, that al thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to paſſe, by fatal deſtinie. Naie ſurely. For
<pb facs="tcp:5636:25"/> thoſe fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de philoſophers taught, that al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges comme to paſſe by the copulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of cauſes wrapped one in another. And they made god ſubiect to this ordre / and row of cauſes depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, after ſuch ſorte, as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere deuiſed his chaine, whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to he tieth Iup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piter alſo. But we ſaie not, that al thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to paſſe, for that the cauſes ar ſo licked to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that one thinge neceſſarely draweth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but bicauſe god hath thorough his ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te wil, and purpoſe, ordained al thinges ſo to be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ther be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And we make not god ſubiecte to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ained, and lincked cauſes, but we make al cauſes. and al thinges ſubiecte to god.</p>
               <p>This than that our aduerſaries wold fraie vs withal, was nothing, but lightninge out of a baſin.</p>
               <p>After that I had gon this far, two other reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theirs, were brought vnto me, wh ch though thei maie be confuted, by that, that I haue al readie ſaid, yet I wil examine them, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I heare / that they acknowlege moſt ſtrength to be in them. The firſt is this. If it had ben goddes wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, than Adam ſhuld haue wanted free wil / but god gaue him free wil / to kepe his commaund m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t if he wold, ergo it was not goddes wil / that he ſhuld ſinne. This reaſon ſhineth to
<pb facs="tcp:5636:25"/> them, as it were gold, but in dede it is but gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted latin. For goddes wil / and ordinance let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted not, but that Adam ſhuld do frely, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly without compulſion that he did, nether did Adam ſinne, thorough want of free wil, &amp; natural ſtrength. If anie did affirme / that god compelled Adam to ſinne, than complaint might be made that Adam wanted free wil.</p>
               <p>And a reaſon might be framed againſt vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adams free wil. But if god ordained, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, without compulſion / tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough his awne faute, and abuſe of his free wil, than this reaſon hath no maner of force / and the complainte is made without cauſe.</p>
               <p>But you wil ſaie, that there was no fault in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam / if that were neceſſarely to be don, that he did. I denie the conſequence. For if he did willyngly breake goddes commaundment, as it is euident, without compulſion / there was a fault great enough in him. The diuel doeth thoſe thinges neceſſarely, that he doeth / and can not chooſe but do them, yet bycauſe he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them willingly without compulſion / tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the rage of his nawghtie wil, he is iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be damned. So though Adam did that muſt nedes be don, yet bycauſe he did it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compulſion, thorough a manifeſt fault of his awne, he deſerued damnation. For it is
<pb facs="tcp:5636:26"/> not al one to do a thinge of neceſſite, and to do a thinge of conſtraint. For god doeth good neceſſarely, and can not do otherwiſe, and yet he doth not good conſtrainedly. The diuel / as I ſhewed you doth euil neceſſarely, and can do none other, and yet he doeth not the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrainedly, but moſt willingly. And thus ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther man, nor diuel can excuſe their faulte, by goddes ordinance, and by neceſſitee. For god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ordinances co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth nether man, nor diuel, to do il, and ſo leaueth a place to their awne fau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. For thei do that thei moſt deſire, and wold do none otherwiſe to chooſe. If men wil ſee this, thei muſt put of the old ſpectacles of fleſhlie bleared eyes, and deſire of god a new ſight, and to be made aegleeyed of him. Heare now the ſeconde argument. Sinne, and death / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in to the world by the enuie of the diuel, and the nawghtie concupiſcence of Adam in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing goddes commaundment, but the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of the diuel, and the nawghtie concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of Adam, were contrarie to goddes wil / ergo it was not goddes wil / that Adam ſhuld ſinne. I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that Adams nawhhtie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, and the diuels enuie, ar contrarie to goddes wil, if you meane by goddes wil, that god neuer alowed, ether the diuels enuie, or Adams nawghtie concupiſcence. But wil
<pb facs="tcp:5636:26"/> you ſaie this / death camme into the world, by the enuie of the diuel, ergo it was not ordained by god? Who than ordained death, whether god wold or no? Did god / as Eſaie teacheth ordaine gehenna, from yeſter daie, that is to ſaie, from eternitee, and not death? As death than came not in to the world beſides goddes ordinance, and yet god delighteth not in death, as it is only death, but as it is the iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinners, ſo ſinne camme not in to the world beſides goddes ordinance / and yet god delighteth not in ſinne, as it is ſinne / but in that, that he wil turne ſinne vnto. You ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue heard the reaſons, that thei thincke maie be made againſt me, heare now how thei diſſolue my reaſons, made againſt them. In which matter thei feately diſcharge them ſelues, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much labor. For thei medel but with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of myn, thother that thei ſaie is myn, cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me out of their awne ſhoppes, and was neuer made by me. To ſhew that Adams ſinne, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me not to paſſe, beſides goddes ordinance, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged this ſentence of. S. Auguſtine. Euen in this, that thei did againſt goddes wil, goddes wil was fulfilled vpon them. Theſe wordes, ſaie thei, make againſt your aſſertion. For Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine ſaieth that the angels apoſtates, &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam did that, that god wold not. But I
<pb facs="tcp:5636:27"/> praie you, what ſaie thei to this, that. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine ſaieth, that by the ſame their acte, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wil was fulfilled vpon them? Here thei giue them ſelues, and vs leaue / and ſpace enough, to breathe. Thei cutte the band in ſondre, where the knotte is not, as for the knotte it ſelfe, thei neuer touche, &amp; yet wold haue men to weene, that thei haue verie wel looſed it.</p>
               <p>The argument, which thei forge them ſelues, &amp; faine to be myne, is this. Nothinge can be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world beſides the wil of god, ſinne is a thinge, ergo it is not don beſide the wil of god.</p>
               <p>In this argument, thei denie the minor, &amp; ſaie that ſinne is nothing. If I ſhuld haue made a ſyllogiſme, I wold haue framed it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſorte. Nothinge in the world is do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides goddes wil, and ordinance, that Adam ſinned was a thinge don in the world, ergo it was don by goddes wil, and ordinance. In the minor, whan I ſaie, that Adam ſinned, I meane Adams ſinful action, and dede, and, not the qualitee only of Adams minde, but in their minor / ſinne ſignifieth only a qualitee / &amp; not an action. Howbeit I maie alſo ſaie truly of Adams ſinne, meaninge the qualitee, or what ſoeuer you wil cal it, that it was not in him, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides goddes wil, and ordinance, though god cauſed it not, &amp; than frame the ſyllogiſme after
<pb facs="tcp:5636:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> this ſorte. Al that was in Adam, was in him, by godddes goddes wil, &amp; ordinance, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne was in Adam, ergo it was in him by god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wil, and ordinance. For it is not al one / to ſaie, that ſinne was in Adam by goddes wil and ordinance, and to ſaie / that ſinne was in A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam, by goddes propre worckinge. The firſt ſaiyng is verie true, and aſcribeth no faulte to god. The ſeconde is verie falſe, for it aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the faulte of Adams fal, to god, From which affirmation, I moſt erneſtly abhorre.</p>
               <p>And I wold to God I might be once halfe ſo far from other faultes, as I am far from that frantike imagination, and droncken dreame of diuelliſh men. Where thei ſaie, that ſinne is nothinge, you ſhal vndreſtand, that in ſcoles this word, nothing, is taken two waies, for nothing negatiuely, and for nothinge priuatiue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. To ſaie, that ſinne is nothinge negatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is open blaſphemie. For ſo men ſhuld be damned for nothinge at al. But thei take this word, nothinge, for nothinge priuatiuely, and teache, that ſinne is a priuation, and abſence of righteouſnes / which is a deſtruction of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, for which god abhorreth the creature, that is defiled therewith. I graunt thei meane ſo, and teach ſo, and ſo meaneth. S. Auguſtine to / but ſeinge the vnlerned can not make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb facs="tcp:5636:28"/> and diſtinction of nothinge negatiuely, and nothinge priuatiuely, nor can wel vndre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande what priuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, though thei be taught, that darcknes is the priuation of light, &amp; death of life, our ariſtarches ſhuld leaue thoſe termes to ſcoles, and teach the people, as the truth is, and as thei maie eaſely vndreſtand, that ſinne is a qualitee repugnant, and contrarie to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des lawes. For thei ar better acquainted with this word qualitee, than with this worde pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And logicians permitte, that priua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions ſhalbe referred to the ſame predicament / that thoſe thinges be in, whereunto thei ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries. As for exemple, darcknes is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to light / and light is a qualitee, therefore darcknes ſhalbe referred to the ſame houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to righteouſnes / &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes is a qualitee, therefore we ſhal putte ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame predicament / and row, that r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſnes is in / &amp; ſaie, that ſinne is a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litee whereby mannes nature is corrupte / &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de worthie to be caſt awaie / and condemned of god. But now theſe good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning, &amp; giue vs good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bid vs be warie, and forbeare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thinges, as the wicked maye turne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But ſo we ſhal ceaſe to preache <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>mercies of god. For wicked men turne
<pb facs="tcp:5636:28"/> that to euil. For the papiſtes ſaie, that by prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chinge of goddes mercies / we encourage men to ſinne. And ſome wicked men perchaunce take occaſion thereby in dede, to ſinne the more boldly. But thei plaie the ſophiſters and take non cauſam pro cauſa. For the verie cauſe in dede of mennes corrupte behauior is their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde boiling ſinful luſt, and not our preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we maie not forbeare to ſpeake the truth, bicauſe euil men can wringe thinges to euil purpoſes. But now lette vs comme to the leſſon, that theſe good ſcolemaſters haue gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, whereby ye ar taught to ouerthrow ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely, and whithout ſweate, whatſoeuer we can allege / for the maintenance of our ſentence.</p>
               <p>For whan it is ſaid, that it was goddes wil, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſinne, you muſt ſaie, that god ſuffred Adam to ſinne, and ſo forth. But theſe ſufferers / that turne al goddes doinges, in to ſuffringes / preately ſuffre them ſelues to be begiled, if thei weene, that manie wil ſtreight waie beleue them. For ſhal we ſaie, that god ſuffred the Iues to conſpire Chriſtes death / whan the holie goſt ſaieth, his hand foreordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it? Whan Micha ſaieth to Ahab. Lo the lord hath giuen the ſpirite of liyng in to the mouth, of al thy prophetes / is that nothinge els but god hath ſuffred thy prophetes to lie?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:29"/>
               <p>Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god biddeth the liyng ſpirite to go, and to deceaue Ahab / I trow / he doeth more / than ſuffre him to go. I ſaie not this, as though this word ſuffringe might nowaie be aſcribed to god, but I ſaie, that thei ar euil ſcolemaſters / that teach you to turne al goddes doinges in to ſuffringes, and yet teache you not in what ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, you ſhal take the word ſuffringe. For ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe is taken ſondrie waies. We maie ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre a thinge with our wil, and we maie ſuffre a thinge againſt our wil. He ſuffreth alſo a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to be don, that meddleth not at al with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And he ſuffreth a thinge to be don, that is contente, and agreeth, that it ſhal be don.</p>
               <p>If thei ſaie / that god ſufferd Adam to ſinne, as one that wold not medle with the matter / that is plaine ſacrilege, and robbeth god of his honor. If thei wolde ſignifie in ſaiyng / that god ſuffred Adam to ſinne, that he was not the propre worcker, and autor of his ſinne / but ordained Adam to ſinne, by Satans propre worckinge, and his awne faulte, than thei mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, as we meane. And than their meruail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous high leſſon is vaniſhed in to ſmoke.</p>
               <p>Now to make at ende, thus I truſt you ſee that I ſtand vnwounded, and vnhurte againſt theſe ſore blodie blowes. If anie man thincke, that I haue ben to quicke againſt them / that be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries
<pb facs="tcp:5636:29"/> in wordes, and not in meaning, lette him conſidre, that I haue not had reſpecte to them only, but alſo to the papiſtes, which er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly vſe the ſame weapons againſt vs.</p>
               <p>And further, bycauſe I trauail to mainteyne the glorie of my god, which ſhineth to the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellyng of wicked mennes yes in the hole gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the world, I thought good to vſe ſome quicknes / and liuelines of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / to awake the dulnes of my hearers. God our moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lord, and father encreaſe the knowlege of his prouidence in vs al, arme vs with patience in theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and confirme in vs, the hope of a better ſtate. Amen, amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:30"/>
               <p>¶ An expoſition of theſe wordes (Leade vs not in to tentation.) made by Bar. Traheron, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge before theſe former lectures, &amp; now added hereto, that you maie know, that he neuer ſaide nor thought that god is the autor of ſinne, as ſome moſt falſly, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly, wold haue men to weene.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reading">
               <p>LEade vs not &amp;) God tempteth, and trieth men ſondrie waies, and to ſondrie endes. Firſt to beginne with his awne, whom he choſe in Chriſt Ieſus, and prepared to euerbaſtinge life before the fundations of the world were laied, he tempteth and trieth them to ſondrie endes, namely ether to make theyr vertues which he him ſelfe hath wrought in them, to ſhine forth more clearely, or to open their ſhame, and nawghtie corrupte nature / that ſo afterwarde thei maie liue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greater wari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and feare of god / and more erneſtly deſire his helpe, knowinge better their awne wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. To the ende, whereof, we ſpake firſt, he tempted Abraham, &amp; Iob to bringe, I mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, their vertues to light, and to make them
<pb facs="tcp:5636:30"/> more certainly knowen. To thother ende, he tempted kinge Dauid, and. S. Petre, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other, not vtterly to deſtroie them, but to humble them / to teach them to know, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre their awne wickednes, and to fele more certainly, his great goodnes, and mercie.</p>
               <p>And though god uſe this temptation to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite of his choſen, yet thei ought to praie, that thei maie not fal in to it. For though it be ſo, that god of his great goodnes, maketh our nawgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines to turne to his glorie / and our welth, yet the godlie ought to abhorre, to committe anie thinge / whereby their god is iuſtly offended.</p>
               <p>But you wil ſaie / if he be offended with tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe our dedes / why bringeth he vs in to them?</p>
               <p>With our dedes he is ſurely offended, but he is delighted with that, that he bringeth to paſſe by them, namely with our humilitee, with our better knowlege of our awne weaknes, &amp; with our more warie walking afterwarde in due fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of him. This tentation, in to which God bringeth his electe / endureth but a time.</p>
               <p>But he bringeth ſome in to a perpetual tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / vtterly giuinge them vp to Satan, &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dening them in wickednes for euer. The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie do not praie / that thei maie not be led in to this temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For thei haue a ſure confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that thei ar goddes children. For otherwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:5636:31"/> thei might not cal him father. And if thei thincke, that thei be goddes children, thei muſt thincke / that thei be goddes choſen. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei be goddes choſen / thei muſt thinke, that thei can be no more damned / than god can ceaſe to be god. For who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath choſen for euer. Nether ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te him of the thinge, that he hath once purpoſed / nor chaunge his purpoſe. For that ſhuld argue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me imperfection in him / which can not be in the diuine nature. Wherefore the godlie ar out of daunger, and feare of this tentation.</p>
               <p>For thei beleue not only that god is their father, but that he wil euer be their father. For he is father to none, ſauing to thoſe, whom he in fallibly choſe before the fundations of the world were laied, whom in tyme he giueih to his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be ſaued / and preſerued for euer. For no man can take them out of his hande, &amp; tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that comme to him, he caſteth not out.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſith noman, nor diuel can take them out of his hand by force / and ſith he hath no wil to caſt them out / thei ar ſafe / and ſure for euer. But here riſeth a great difficulte. For it ſemeth vniuſt, that god ſhuld leade ſome in to temptation, and harden them / and giue them vp for euer to ſinne / and yet puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſinnes. Neuertheles we ſaie, that god lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:5636:31"/> into tentation / not only whereby mennes vertues ar brought to light, or their weaknes uttered / to their welth, which happeneth to the choſen, but alſo whereby thei ar hardened / and made ſtiffer in their wickednes / and giuen vp to ſinne, which happeneth to the reprobate. And that this is ſo, the ſcripture teacheth plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, where we haue, that god hardened Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os herte / and gaue vp idolatres to ſhameful raging luſtes, and where it is ſaid, to the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the goſpel. Go, and engroſſe the her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of this people, make dul their eares, ſtoppe their eyes, that thei ſe not / with their eyes &amp;c. Certaine writers, bycauſe thei can not ſee how this maie be don iuſtly / alter the toun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the holie goſt, and for lead vs not / they ſaie, ſuffre vs not to be led / and where god ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth / he hardened Pharao, thei ſaie, he ſuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to be hardened. And ſo in teaching the holie goſt to ſpeake, thei thincke, that they haue auoided al abſurditee, and inconuenience.</p>
               <p>But ſo in dede thei auoide one inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience with another, yea with an inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / thei runne from the truth. Other better lerned ſaie, that god is greater, than mannes reaſon, ſo that it is no meruail, if we can not ſee his iudgementes thoroughly. For often tymes / the deuiſes of verie wiſe men, ſeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt,
<pb facs="tcp:5636:32"/> and vnwiſe to vs at the beginninning, &amp; yet whan we ſee the iſſue, and end of them, we ar compelled, to confeſſe / that thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were righteouſely don / that we at the firſt thought to be foliſh. So whan we ſhal entre in to goddes ſanctuarie, and ſe god, as he is / we ſhal perceaue that he neuer did anie thinge / vniuſtly, or vnreaſonably / but that he hath delt with al men according to the vtter moſt point ether of equitee, or of mercie. Al this is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie truly ſpoken. How beit, I ſee not, but that euen in this life, we maie ſee good, and iuſt cauſes, that god ſhuld harden the reprobate / and leade them in to this baleful temptation. For ar not they worthie to be hardened? And what vnrighteouſnes is it, to harden the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ar worthie to be hardened? For you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſtande, that whan the ſcripture ſaieth, that god hardeneth men, the meaning is not / that thei were ſoft before, and that than god harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them / for whan were thei ſoft? But the meaning is, that god maketh them harder.</p>
               <p>And that is iuſtly don. For their former hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deſerued to be made harder. In dede if thei had ben ſoft before / and than hardened by god, there had ben ſome place left to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint.</p>
               <p>But if god puniſh their former hardnes, with more hardnes, he dealeth with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, moſt iuſtly.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5636:32"/>
               <p>This beinge conſidered / that the reprobate ar neuer ſoft, but euer hard, as it is euident, I ſee not ſo great difficultie in the matter. For why ſhuld not god harden them / that ar wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be hardened / by reaſon of their former hardnes? Why ſhuld not god leade them in to perpetual temptation, and giue them ouer for euer, that ar worthie to be led in to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al tentation, and to be giuen ouer for euer? If anie man wil ſaie, that it is goddes faulte, that he ſofteneth not al men, lette him ſhew, that god firſt hardened al men. If al men firſt harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them ſelues / what ſhal conſtraine him to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoft againe? If he wil, he ſheweth his mercie / if he wil not, he ſheweth his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. But who ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelle him to ſhew his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, where he maie ſhew his iuſtice? If than he harden, he doth iuſtly, if he ſoften, he doeth mercifully. By knowlege hereof, the godlie ſhal haue this profite, that thei ſhal much more haue in reuerent admiration, the exceding gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at goodnes of god, whan thei ſhal conſidre / that he vouchſafed to take them in to the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of thoſe, whom of his mercie he wold ſofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where of his iuſtice he might haue hardened them for euer. Thus I truſt, I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you iuſt cauſes, why god hardeneth ſome, &amp; leadeth them in to ſuch tentation, as bringeth
<pb facs="tcp:5636:33"/> with it euerlaſting deſtruction. Howbeit I denie not / but that in manie worckes of god / before we can iudge rightly, we muſt tarie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we maie ſee them altogether, and not by pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For there be manie thinges amonge vs here in this world, which we ſhuld iudge il fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored, if we ſhuld ſee but peeces of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which being ſeen together / ar moſt comelie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>autiful. So if we we wil ſee the decent, and comelie ordre of goddes doinges, we muſt ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie, til we maie ſee the hole bodie together, and not a legge in one place, &amp; an arme in another a mile of, and the head, as far diſtant. But we maie not paſſe thus from this matter. For there be ſome ſentences of the ſcripture, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to impugne our ſaiynge, and to teach partly that god tempteth no man, partly that he temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth no man to vttre deſtruction. Touching the firſt. S. Iames ſaieth, lette no man, whan he is tempted, ſaie, that he is tempted of god. For as god can not be tempted of euil, ſo he te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth noman. But euerie man is tempted, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le he is drawen awaie, and baited with his aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne luſt. To this I ſaie, that. S. Iames meaneth plainly, that god tempteth noman, as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and worcker of ſinne in him. For god cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not euil in a mannes herte, and than ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him to committe that euil in acte, that he
<pb facs="tcp:5636:33"/> hath cauſed and wrought in him, but where as man is euil of him ſelfe / thorough Adams fal, and ful of vices, by his awne corrupte nature / god ſtirreth him to vttre thoſe ſecrete ſores, not that god made, but that man had / by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and poiſoning his nature, which god at the beginning made good. So it is tru, that god tempteth noman to euil, which he hath not, but god maketh him vttre the euil / which he hath / and as it were, pulleth the adder out of his hoale. And who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaie that, that is not wel, and iuſtly don? After this vndreſtanding I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. S. Iames wordes. For I wil not make hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſette his head, and to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne againſt the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſcriptures. For who hath not red theſe wordes, in the .24. of the .2. boke of kinges. God<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des anger encreaſed againſt Iſrael / and he ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp Dauid againſt them, to ſaie, go, and no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre Iſrael, and Iehuda. For by that acte / as it appeareth, Dauid greatly and iuſtly offended god / and brought a ſore plage vpon him ſelfe / and vpon the people. For Dauid ſurely would truſt in the multitude of his people, leauinge the confidence / that he ought to haue had in God only. Therefore the ſcripture ſaieth, that god ſtirred him to nombre his people / to make his nawghtie diſtruſt in god knowen, and to puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he the people which had offended him with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their
<pb facs="tcp:5636:34"/> ſinnes. Howbeit god was not the autor / and worcker of Dauides diſtruſt, nor of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples ſinne / but moued Dauid to ſhew forth that / whereby al the world might ſe, that god iuſtly puniſhed him. Againe we haue in the 12. of the .2. boke of kinges, theſe wordes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ſaieth god, by the prophete Nathan, to Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid after he had committed abominable adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſlaine innocent Vrie, I ſtirre vp euil vpon the, out of thine awne houſe, &amp; I wil ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thy wiues in thy ſight, &amp; deliuer them to thy neighbor, and he ſhal lie with thy wiues / in the ſight of this ſunne. For thou haſt wrought in ſecrete, but I wil do this thinge before al Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael &amp; Now though it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to paſſe by god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ordinance, that Abſolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laie openly with Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uides wiues, yet it is plaine, that god wrought not in Abſolom that vile adulterous minde, but vſed that nawghtie minde, that Abſolom had, to puniſh Dauides ſhameful adulterie, &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Touchinge the ſeconde matter, that god tempteth no man to euerlaſtinge damnation, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me allege the prophete Ezechiel, where god ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. I wil not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhal turne, and liue. And. S. Paule to Timothee. God wil haue al men to be ſaued.</p>
               <p>To theſe ſcriptures, this is myn aunſwer. Where god ſaieth in Ezech. that he wil not the
<pb facs="tcp:5636:34"/> death of a ſinner, we muſt vndreſtand it of thoſe ſinners, whom he hath choſen before the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge of the world to be conuerted, &amp; to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. For it is euident by. S. Paule that god hath ſome veſſels of wrath, ordained to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; therefore he giueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp for euer to wallow in their ſinnes, and in them puniſheth one ſinne with another. If anie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke it vniuſt, that god ſhuld ordaine ſome to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; puniſh ſinne with ſinne let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew, that thei were not worthie / to be ordained to deſtruction, and to be ſo puniſhed. God than wil not the life, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of thoſe, whom he hath appointed to deſtruction. For than his wil ſhuld be againſt his awne decree. Wherefore, as I ſaid, we muſt vndreſtand, that he willeth the life, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſion of them, whom he hath appointed to ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; of none other. For whan ſainct Luke ſaieth / that as manie beleued; as were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to euerlaſtinge life / he teacheth thereby, that the reſt, which beleued not, were neuer appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to euerlaſtinga life. And who can ſaie / that it is goddes wil to ſaue anie / beſides his awne appointment? If anie man wil take theſe wordes, god willeth not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, for god delighteth not ſimply and abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely in the death of a ſinner, but for a certaine reſpecte / the hebrue word, kaphets, which Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel
<pb facs="tcp:5636:35"/> vſeth is, ſhal fauor &amp; helpe their vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. I know i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dede what maner of obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome rauinge vnlerned ſpirites make againſt this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſtanding / but it maie be aſſone co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed / as reherſed. For thei ſaie, that god willeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge, wherein he delighteth not. For wil ſaie thei, being a power of the mind, which hath hir free worcking in chooſing, and deſiring / or in refuſing, and not willing, willeth nothinge but that wherein it delighteth. Theſe ſeelie ſoules can not make a difference betweene wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a thinge for it ſelfe, &amp; willinge of a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge for a certaine purpoſe, and not for it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>If their ſaiyng were tru, men in a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt might not caſt their goodes in to the ſea, for ſauing of their awne lyues, onles thei delighted in the loſſe of their goodes. Iudges might not wil theues to be hanged / onles thei delighted in their hanginge, and ſo the firſt poore men ſhuld be verie noddies and al iudges plaine murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. Yea ſo thei affirme that god cold haue no wil that his ſonne ſhuld be tormented, onles he delighted in his torment. And than thei ſaie ether / that Chriſt was crucified whether God wold or no / and againſt his decreed wil &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or els thei aſſigne to god, that I abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to vttre for the falſnes of it, and abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But we wil combre our ſelues no farther
<pb facs="tcp:5636:35"/> with ſuch dotinges, of brainſicke men.</p>
               <p>Touchinge the wordes of Ezechiel thei maie be alſo ſhortely thus vndreſtanded, that goddes wil is not / that anie ſinner conuerted / and repentant / ſhal die. Where Sainct Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſaieth, that god wil al men to be ſaued, he figh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth not againſt himſelfe, but meaneth that god hath choſen ſome of al ſortes, and ſtates, whom he wil bringe to the knowlege of his truth.</p>
               <p>But bicauſe we can not know certainly which thei be, S. Paule biddeth vs praie for al ſortes of men, for kinges / and noble men, which yet ſeme farthieſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, and godlines. For god amonge al ſortes of men, hath ſome whom he wil ſaue. And this is no new expoſition / though new men vſe it. For this is an old worne, and wel knowen ſentence. Diſtributio eſt, non pro ſingulis generum, ſed pro generi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſingulorum, quia de qualibet conditione ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minum aliquos predeſtinauit ad vitam. Which wordes teach / that goddes wil is to appointe to life, and ſaue ſome of euerie ſorte, and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not euerie one of al ſortes and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And ſurely it is mere madnes, to ſaie, that god wil ſaue more, than his ſonne wold praie for. The wordes of his ſonne / whoſe wil agreeth with the fathers in al thinges, ar wel knowen. I praie not for the world, ſaieth he, but
<pb facs="tcp:5636:36"/> for thoſe, whom thou haſt giuen me. Why it is not goddes wil / to ſaue al, I know not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly / that it is not his wil I know, and I know that whom ſoeuer he condemneth, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth iuſtly. And herein I appeale to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of al men. For no man liuinge in the world, can auoide, but that he ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that there is in him moſt iuſt matter, and moſt iuſt cauſes of damnation. For al men ar defiled with ſinne, &amp; ſinne was not in them by their creation, but thei pulled it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, &amp; wrought it in them ſelues, declining from their firſt ſtate. So al men ar worthie, to be left in the puddel of the filthie ſinnes wherein thei ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue willingly drouned them ſelues, &amp; in the end to be damned. And ſo god is iuſt, if he giue them ouer in this life to the wickednes, whereof the verie cauſe, and roote is in them ſelues, by their awne procurement, &amp; if he appoint them to euerlaſting puniſhment after this life, which thei haue iuſtly deſerued thorough their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold horrible offences. Now I wolde tarie you no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, ſauinge that as often as we ſpeake of this matter / rude men ruſh in / and thincke to roote vp al with their twifold ſnouttes. For if it be ſo that, god hath al readie foreappointed whom he wil ſaue, and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wil condemne, than ſaie thei, preachinges and exhortations be
<pb facs="tcp:5636:36"/> vaine, and ſuperfluous, and it ſtilleth not how men liue. For the reprobate can no waie be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and the choſen can no waie be damned.</p>
               <p>Hereunto the godlie ſhal aunſwer, firſt that it is not ſuperfluous to preache to the reprobate / for thereby their damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made iuſter, and thei ar driuen farther fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al excuſe. And to the choſen it is right fruteful. For thereby it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth god to awake their ſlepie ſluggiſhnes, &amp; to quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their dul me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. For god worcketh two waies in them, by his ſpirite within, &amp; by his worde without. By his ſpirite he lighteneth their darcke mindes / and new frameth their cro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked hertes. By his word he ſpurreth them fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarde / &amp; inflameth them to deſire, &amp; to ſeke newnes of life. If than god wil vſe his worde as an inſtrument, whan he wil ſhew the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, &amp; mightie worckinge of his hand, with what face can anie man ſaie, that preaching is ſuperfluous to the choſen? If god wil that waie prepare them to his farther worcking in them / ſhal anie man forbidde him, to vſe the meane / that ſemeth good to him? Secondly / where thei ſaie, that it ſhal not ſkil how men liue, we wil deſire them to vnderſtand / that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, thorough their wicked life, &amp; heaping of ſinne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne make their damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more greuous. And as for the choſen thei
<pb facs="tcp:5636:37"/> findie not in dede to liue wel, that thei maie wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne heauen, but thei ſtudie to liue wel, bicauſe hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen is alreadie theirs. Thei labor not to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues goddes childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorough good worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, but bicauſe thei be goddes children there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thei worcke wel. Thei ſaie not bicauſe we ar alreadie ſaued, we wil do not good workes, but thei ſaie, bicauſe we ar ſaued therefore we wil ſtudie to do good worckes, and to ſhew our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues thanckeful to him / who of his only mercie hath ſaued vs. For thei know that thei ar appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to goddes ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdome, &amp; ſaued to this e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that thei ſhuld glorifie their heauenlie father tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough good workes, &amp; be faſhioned after the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his ſonne, &amp; not to wallow themſelues in filthie luſtes, but to liue in puritee, &amp; holines before god their ſaueor, who renueth, &amp; refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth al thoſe with his holie ſpirite, whom he hath foreordained to enioie his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly. Wherefore theſe wild bores weare their tuſkes inuaine againſt this adama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which maie be hitte, but neuer hurte. This much I had to ſaie to you at this tyme, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue god the glorie. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>This note, .i., ſtandeth for, that is to ſaie. In the end of the .2. reading for, let ſaie, reade / let vs ſaie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Anno. 1558.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5636:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
